so we're gonna get started I'm calling the March 11th traffic Commission meeting to order thank you very much for all joining we have we have a one or two people who are not present but we do have a quorum so we are going to go forward the first item on the agenda is the minutes of the previous meeting the
January meeting I'll make a motion to approve the January 2025 meeting minutes
I'll second so there's been a motion in a second is there any further discussion hearing none all in favor say aye aye any opposed the motion carries thank you very much the next item is staff project updates Cindy do we have any of those
that we want to share um yes we have um i'm not sure if they were distributed or not mindy the the update um we have sort of a spreadsheet that we're providing each month to the commission related to various projects that the um public works is working on related to um streets and um in our in the city so last month i provided um a spreadsheet that includes a list of uh the projects that we're currently working on i can just go through a couple of these just to highlight things that have changed since the last meeting um the ann and juniata streetscape project we did receive some additional funding for that project so we now have close to a million dollars and we are kicking off with the consultant later this month to identify what the scope uh what we can include with that you know that kind of funding in the scope so again that was a lot of safety improvement you know a safety improvement at the ann and juniata intersection and then also looking at improving sidewalks and lighting in that area on juniata and and street um the manor street traffic signal project if we go down halfway through the the list there we are currently under construction um for that and that's replacing traffic signals at new dillard um pearl and ruby and um along manor street so we're updating the traffic signals and that's happening right now um the plum street roundabout i know the commission received information about a sign that was knocked down there um that project you know that sign has um we may replace it with some other uh delineators because the sign keeps getting hit i know if you've been out to plum street the the work isn't quite complete they had to shut down for the winter and signs and pavement markings weren't all completely installed or and the paving actually so hopefully in the next month or two those were all being installed and you'll see a completed project out there the queen and farnum intersection improvement that's where we're adding some bump outs some a flashing beacons and we're also doing some green infrastructure at that intersection that will be going out to bid in the next month or so so that will be under construction this summer and then the south duke street mobility project where we are doing improvements along south duke street and including a shared use path along the side of south duke and adding back in diagonal parking on the west side of the street and trying to improve a lot of the pedestrian crossings in that area that we received bids today so we'll be reviewing those and hopefully awarding that in the next month or so so construction will start on south duke street as well and then um just to highlight the street design guidelines and the two-way conversion those were all those are both projects related to the safe streets for all grant that we received and we are kicking those off so we should be going out to the public probably in the june early summer time frame with some preliminary analysis and discussion with the public about those projects and then finally the residential permit parking program we are working with lpa to collect occupancy data they have the license plate reader equipment that is being tested and once we have more information related to the occupancy data so knowing how much parking is being used during specific time periods then we'll be able to go out back out to the public for those pilot areas that were identified and start to have discussion about how to address our PP in those areas very good thank you very much are
there any questions on the Commission on any of these projects and Cindy you had said that this is available on the website as well is this updated on the
website I don't believe it's available on the website but that is something we could provide on the vision zero website actually we could add that to the vision
in many ways we're looking at this is an enhancement of another way to communicate with the public on what is going on and what is being done in the public right-of-way so if we can do that that would be great and I thank you for the for the update next we'll go to the action agenda the first item is old business item 51 2024 considering the request of Kevin Rolfes to add a con I'm sorry of kevin rolfs to add a convex mirror to the intersection of north plum street and reynolds avenue is mr rolfs present ben is this something that you're updating us on so staff member ben
hogan will be updating us oh good afternoon commission uh my name is ben hogan i'm a public works engineer for city of lancaster so this one uh plum and reynolds was before you at the last meeting. The initial request was for a convex safety mirror to see approaching traffic. Because of a site distance issue, we no longer install convex safety mirrors. It's not an approved treatment. So we looked at some parking removal instead to get adequate sight lines at this intersection. Last time we had proposed removing some parking at the intersection, particularly nearly 40 feet on the north side, on the northwest corner, and about 36 and 1 half feet on the southeast corner for adequate visibility. The commission had requested more public outreach. So since the last meeting, we've reached out to residents within a two-block area radius of this intersection that might travel through or park at the intersection. We sent letters to both property owners and tenants in English and Spanish. I got one response. I provided them with my email, phone number, and an invitation to today's meeting. The one response I did get was a resident that lived about a block away on Marshall Street. And she was with our idea. She wanted to see parking removed to have improved visibility. So I didn't receive any other public comment. Just looking for your action at this time, if you feel it's appropriate to implement this restriction.
Mindy, are you able to turn this so that we can see the actual intersection? And Sergeant and Philip, you can move up this so that you can see the diagrams close up to you. Very good. Thank you, Mindy. So Ben, you're proposing where this blue car is, that that would be?
Yes, we would take parking back to where that existing sign post is right now. It's around 36 and 1 half feet to that existing signpost, about 1 and 1 half parking spaces. And then on the north side of that intersection, we're proposing to take 40 feet for adequate visibility. And we're also considering adding a pedestrian crossing there in the future. There's a ramp on the other side that's already been constructed, so we just need to construct one on this side. And that parking restriction would line up nicely if we chose to move forward with that in the future.
So in essence, in order to provide that kind of visibility, we would be losing approximately 3 and 1 half spaces.
Total, yes.
Are there any questions from the commission or further discussion about the site from the commission?
You mentioned that in the future you might add another ramp and a crosswalk. Is that a future project just because it involves more cost than putting up the signs?
Yeah, there's a few complications here. There's a tree at that corner that's very close to the corner that might need some work. There's also a stormwater inlet there. Whenever we're adding ramps, we have to consider when we lower the curb also moving those inlets. So it can add up to be quite a bit of cost. We certainly want to finish that pedestrian crossing. Just looking to add that to a future contract. That's not exactly lined up at this time.
How have we looked at it?
We have. Yeah, so we looked at reportable crash data over the past five years. The five available years were 2019 to the end of 2023. There were two reportable crashes at the intersection. Both incidents involved vehicles on Reynolds Avenue proceeding without clearance into the intersection. So that kind of supported our initiative to improve sight lines at the intersection. It seems like those incidents could have been resolved by improved sight lines.
Any further questions? Any recommendations? Any motions?
I move that we adopt the recommendation to remove the parking spots. Yes, you may. I move that we adopt the recommendation to remove the parking spots.
There's a motion. Is there a second? Second. A motion and a second. Is there any further discussion? At the commission level? At the level of the public? Is anyone from the public want to speak on the side? Hearing none, all in favor of approving has been proposed by uh staff say aye aye any opposed the motion carries thank you very very much thank you the next item under old business is item 02 of 2025 considering the request of jason stauffer of eckland development to add a load zone to either 2-8 south duke street or 46 east king street mr stafford um ben is this something that you're you and your team have taken a look at
yeah i mean i think it's been reviewed was the re did we get an official request i think it was reviewed by please previously was reviewed by within the minutes from the last
meeting right yeah it was reviewed by sort of i think the recommendation was to not deny it and and then the requester wasn't present at the last meeting so correct so i think mr stoffer was not
in attendance sergeant dray stated that he denied this loading zone during site review and stated why director campbell asked if staff had looked at it mr mccormick stated yes but she thought it should wait until mr stoffer was in attendance so he's currently not in attendance we should continue to table this one? I'll make a motion to table. Motion to table? Second. And a second. Any further discussion? All in favor? How many meetings do they not show up for until it's eliminated? The request is not valid anymore. The question is how many meetings does it get tabled for before we just remove it? Because they're not in attendance. Correct. It's a matter of internal policy i would imagine twice so this would remove would remove from the agenda and the person could um submit resubmit at a later date so we're giving them the opportunity right
we're saying they if they don't show up for the next meeting it would be denied and then
they've already missed two yes this is the second one that they've missed okay so do we want to just deny it and have them resubmit yes we're in support of that two two no-shows means a denial and then the person is still free to resubmit but it does not stay alive and if if someone was missed to two meetings in a row so then I would
revise my motion to deny the application so the previous motion has been
withdrawn the new motion is to deny is there a second second denial in a second a motion in a second any further discussion all in favor aye any opposed not opposed motion carries this motion is denied okay now we're back now we're to new business the first item is item 09 2025 considering the request from the lancaster marriott at penn square to renew the designated parking spaces on east king for hotel use and the
requester is mr josh novak yes yes um good afternoon i'm josh novak i'm the general manager for the lancaster marriott and lancaster county convention center and before you as the agenda indicated is the renewal um for utilization of the parking spots uh designated parking spots there on east king street right in front of the hotel and plow restaurant as activity at the hotel and convention center continues to increase these spots are really imperative to help accommodate uh arriving guests for both the hotel and events as you know if you've been downtown our driveway is a bit limited so when there are heavy activity going on there these spots are very very important for us to help unload guests and those who are arriving to the facility it also cuts down tremendously on volume of cars who are coming up queen street towards penn square who are in that turning lane waiting to turn into the driveway so uh we have been leasing them from the lancaster parking authority uh and it continues to be a very important area for us and it is currently legally a loading zone i mean yes we un i don't know the official designation of it but it we use it for loading and unloading yeah it is not it's not used to park it's it's for loading and unloading and we are a 24-hour business so this happens um around the
the clock yeah the answer I would say is absolutely yes it's hard to predict
depending on the composition of events or weekends or things that are going on at the hotel when the heaviest arrivals are in a lot of cases many times we have the entire hotel checking out and the entire hotel checking in and that can take you know throughout the evening so there's not it's very it's not uncommon for me or anybody they say six or seven where we would still have two to three hundred rooms set to still arrive so it's very hard to predict based on the
composition of what's going on throughout the year yes we certainly do
that as well um but that driveway as you probably know is really probably fits four to five cars because you keep a lane open for obviously emergency services so it's sort of an extension
of the driveway and you know very critical i think your question was from the park garage not from
the driveway no so i we do as much as we can um because we don't have valley valley services we do direct people to go right to the Penn Square garage if they're checking in. That's just not a reality, depending on the amount of luggage, the age of the guests who are arriving. So we do try to do that as much as we can.
Okay. Any questions, comments, suggestions, recommendations? Is there a particular reason why you do not do valet parking?
It's still something that's still in consideration post-COVID. being able to staff it but it would still require us to use those areas even more so now that we have the additional tower so now that we're 416 rooms it would that would be even more queuing
for valet services for sure i would just say somebody who has used a hotel i might not have read it ahead of time that I'm supposed to go in the garage initially until I went and got it doesn't surprise me that even if you're trying to get folks to go
to the garage any further questions is there a potential motion I'll make a
motion to approve the request for the Lancaster Marriott Penn Square for renewal of their designated parking space on East King Street for hotel
purposes there's been a motion to approve is there a second i would second a motion and a second is
there further discussion at the commission level i would i would just like to add that um i believe it was three years was that the time frame for is it two or three three i think the stipulation from previous approvals was that it's needed to be renewed every three years so i i think it would
it would be prudent to add that as well so so we're adding that it's renewed you it's valid for three years would require renewal after the third year so in March 2028 yes any further
discussion any discussion from the public parking authority supports the request I'm sorry parking
supports the request all in favor any opposed the motion carries thank you very much the next item under new business is item 10 2025 considering the request of a load zone at Sedro's Airport 358 to 360 North Queen Street is
hello everybody I'm reading the notes here from sergeant race which I thought
he was gonna be here tonight and well he looks like a good man to be on this
board and i originally thought the vote was supposed to be a handicap and one loading zone space and when they did it they only put in the handicap space i think it's been made clear
to you what the what we were putting in as far as a handicap space well it says it right in here in
the notes it was a loading zone it was a handicap and one parking space in what in the minutes i
think there was then it was a dismay note that it needed to be a discussion for you to coordinate with staff after yes and i think we made it clear it was either a handicapped space for a loading
zone that's that's not what i understood and that's even what i even called ben about about
the loading zone i think we talked about the fact was going to be a loading zone on lemon street
and that is why well i sent you pictures of the loading zone on print street has anybody looked at
them the the improvements related to the bike facility aren't complete yet there will be delineators that will be put in the area excuse me that became a four lane parking space up there
and that's and that was a three today and there's four there right now the fire engine couldn't even turn to get down or tractor and trailer cannot turn at that street right now I've had loading zones for 65 years and all of a sudden we're not using
correctly the whole block uses it and I'm paying for it why why was it taken
away? And why is our pushback 20 feet, 9 inches, and on the other side of the street is 14.6?
Why can't it be even? I'm just rereading. It does state that the way Mr. Segru is using the loading zone is not the intended purpose. On the application, which was shown to the audience, stated that any vehicle that is in the process of actively loading on and loading of property may utilize the load zones. Sergeant Drace stated that this is not how Mr. Centro is using the load zone. He also offered to remove the load zone and place a handicapped parking space. Sergeant Drace made a motion to accept items 05-2025 and 06-2025 of the consent agenda, seconded by Mr. Mandros.
When I talked to Sergeant Drace, he never said that to me. I called the mayor's office on it they would not recall so now it's we went to
the district attorney's office on this subject we're talking discussion because
sergeant drays told me something completely different he said it was not up to him and he came out and spoke against me here when I called when I called when this all happened I don't know why after 41 years nobody on the block ever complained and all of a sudden there was a person complaining I'm not complaining about loading zones that are 24 7 7 days a week I'm not asking for something like that which there are in the city I'm not asking for a loading zone in front of the liquor control store which they they load from the side. So it's all retail. So if somebody loses our loading zone, which I pay for, and goes to Lancaster Pickle Company, that's not good if you can't get a parking space on the block. They can't
use a meter. So the loading zones are not, please correct me if I'm wrong, the loading zones are not
for handicapped parking? No, we have one of those. Right, and that was... So we corrected that last time by adding a handicapped space. So I guess here's my challenge. I'm looking at what was in
the minutes and it seems to coincide with my recollection of what was discussed and then you've
gone outside to get a different reading. Is that what I'm understanding? No, I thought just as the minutes, I thought it was opposed, it was instead of two spaces, it got reduced to a handicapped space and a loading zone space if i remember the last meeting correctly i think that ultimately the
request was withdrawn at the meeting and it looks like in the intro there's been a new request that was handled administratively for a handicapped parking spot which has been installed and then another request for a load zone and i see um that the recommendation from summer i believe was to deny it because it seems like a more appropriate space for a load zone would be mid-block.
So you're putting the loading zone that people use on Lemon Street so when the purveyors that go to the Belvedere, they have to cross two intersections
now. Well, it's to be put in a location that tries to serve as many businesses as possible.
There's no business on Lemon Street. There's a lady that does hair, and there's a store. That's the only business that's on Lemon Street.
So the recommendation is on South Queen Street.
It's to move it south.
Can you pull up the picture?
No, south would be, yes, I guess, if you want to call it south, yeah. So there is even another loading zone space at Lemon and Duke, which is not even used anymore. That's used for going to the funerals and the dentist offices and places like that. That's not loading and unloading either. So you have four car parking space on Lemon Street that has no businesses.
Basically, your request to add a loading zone was reviewed by the police, and they indicated that the location you requested would be denied but their recommendation was if a loading zone was needed on that block on the 300 block of north queen street that it should be mid-block put it on mid-block we need a loading
zone and it should be on our side because that's where all the businesses are and that's the
safest place to get off is right onto the payment so mid-block would be closer to the guild that's
fine, just as long as we have a loading zone. We have Airbnbs, we've got antique shops, we've got pickle shops, we've got nail salons, they all get shipments. What people are used to is they're used to the loading zone at this location. That's why I said it'd be more convenient and I'd be willing to pay for
for it you know it's not like I come to meetings all the time so I don't know
what the requests were or how it got changed but but I did after after the final summary of all this went down which I was very new I thought it was a a handicap and adding the loading zone to the behind the handicap section. When Travis Goode came to our place, he said when they were putting the 20.9 setback, he said they would probably add the two parking spaces behind that, and that calmed us down. I mean, we were all upset, you know, without notice and everything else that's happened to us. I think it's not the right way to do business, and I think we should be treating businesses in Lancaster a little bit better than what we're doing here.
If I may, I just want to ask if there's already been a recommendation that a mid-block load zone might be appropriate. Do we need to do this as a commission or?
Or just as an administrative clarification.
Yeah, if that already seems appropriate, then do we need to not do anything?
Why not put it back where it was originally? Can I ask that question?
That's true. May I ask? Let me give you a point of reference that will help you guys.
Can you just come to the microphone?
Larry Cohen, Parking Authority. There was a mid-block loading zone that was paid for by building characters. They had it for several years. Marty gave it up, I think, at least over a year ago. because he stated that folks were just parking there and it wasn't being used as a loading zone. So I just wanted to let you know whatever decision you make, there was a mid-block pretty much in front of building characters. Of course, we need to enforce it, right? So that folks are not just parking there. But in the recent past, there was and it was given up by the building characters who paid for it. So I just wanted to let you know that.
So in essence the recommendation is to revert back to having that loading zone basically in the same location that it previously had been in. I mean it helps
because everybody knows it. The people from out of town, they know it. They go to the Belvedere, the meat guys, the booze guys, you know, they all go there. So it's convenient. Our guys know it. All the postmen, all the drop-off guys to the pickle shop and all that there's all there all that the Korean restaurants they drop they park down there and put their food bring their food up to the restaurant yeah it's I mean you know and it's safer
there restored then we just need to make sure that it is enforced properly so that it is available
for loading as necessary you're referring to the mid block loading zone i just want to make that clear i don't believe that's what necessarily understand i think that's what mr cohn said too the midlock didn't work i don't think he said that he said that cars were parked there but that's something that can be enforced as well yeah it's an enforcement issue well sure sure
i mean we've got the people got tickets there sure so had it been had a hold on just a second
had it been removed had that loading zone been removed or was it just now it's not enforced
so marty from building characters had made the request for that loading zone mid-block on queen and he means he paid for it over the however many years and within the last year or two He said he did not want to pay for the loading zone anymore.
So the mid-block loading zone was removed?
Correct.
So the request then is for it to be restored or for there to be a new mid-block loading zone put in there?
Well, that wasn't the original request, but if you're modifying that request... You've changed the request around. If you want to...
I'm just asking for clarity of what the request is at this point.
It's not my request.
The clarification was that the loading zone would be put back behind the handicap zone.
So you would probably deny that request and approve re-institution of the mid-block?
Which nobody wanted.
Well, we have to enforce it, for sure.
And I just want to clarify, the loading zone was in front of MADCAP, not a building character.
Yeah, it was somewhere in that.
I think Marty was paying for that loading zone that's a whole nother
conversation if he wants to proceed would you I'm sorry I'm not understanding
Would it meet your needs to have a loading zone that's further south than what your initial request was? I understand your initial request was one that's directly south of what's now the handicapped parking spot. And the recommendation was to deny that.
That would be the ideal one because if you want to take a poll of all the…
I understand that that's ideal. Okay. Would you accept? Would it meet your needs to have one that's a little bit further south?
And that's towards the old lab cellars?
Reinstated at that.
The more action is down this way because they can hit the Belvedere, they can hit the store across the street, they can hit all the antiques, and they can hit the gallery, and they change over. They can hit the pop-up shop, and they change constantly.
So would you rather not have a load zone and have one further south?
I would rather bring it back to where it was for 41 years.
That's not an option at this point. Pardon me? That's not an option that's being presented at this point. That was denied based on a site review done by myself as well as traffic.
So would you be okay with it being denied?
Why all of a sudden would it be denied?
Your last request for application has been put in for a low zone in front of your property. I believe it was the 58th.
it was already there for 41 years it was taken away without it's not there now we're going based
on now and the application that was put in it was it was am i putting the application in wrong no you're not putting it okay you have to be completed which it was and that and that site review does not recommend going to be placed where you're requesting it i understand that will be most convenient for you okay however that is not an approved record okay well how do i get a loading zone for the block so that's what we're talking about now we're presenting to you the option of possibly moving and putting a loading zone south of where you're requesting it i i i
said let's go for it okay and that's that's the question but i said the ideal one and then i we
get that okay we understand we understand exactly okay we're all trying to get to the same place i
think so the intention would be to to implement the loading zone further south approximately where can we show is it exactly in front of these buildings or probably where i guess would
should we do another assessment yes and identify so i think if that's the case then it could be
handled like a typical loading zone in that you're identifying i mean in this situation we're identifying the optimal location but it would be done administratively and then it would just come before the commission as a consent agenda item and that would that would be the
loading zone and it would still be a handicap parking space correct that is that that has
been installed and i believe it's on the consent agenda that has been installed the handicap yes
nice pardon me so you did the right thing by requesting clarification and confirmation and although it's not exactly you had hoped for it to be what we're about to act on is likely getting you I shouldn't I shouldn't presume the
vote but is there any further discussion I don't know please tell me what what
just happened go over it one more time and what what's going to happen to confirm that it's appropriate for it to be in that location or in the proposed
closer to mid-life location okay another request doesn't need to be made is that right we'll just handle it as the same that's okay that then with that report
with the confirmation it would be done administratively and it would be under the consent of the consent actions next time as work that will have been done so
when when the approvals are made administratively it doesn't need to come before the commission staff just does that so in this case it's police and our traffic unit will review it and identify the best location and then they can have it installed based on their recommendation and then it just comes to us sort of post after it's been installed for a formal approval so that it's documented in the books basically well the communications
between the traffic commission and the individual there's no emails going back and forth there's no you can't get anybody to talk to you the alder I could never I got Ben accidentally he picked the phone up accidentally to call out and I was on the line I had to tell him that his his mailbox was full he said there's no way that huh and he said there's no way to tell so if you call the mayor's office their mailbox is full sergeant race always answered whenever you called he was always on the ball there but you know other places are not but I still got I still want an answer on the setback at 20.9 to the other setback on the other side of 14.6 what why the difference can somebody
answer that question here but why why is neither block from this block there's no setbacks. So on North Queen Street. So you're parking within 20 feet of a crosswalk based on the vehicle code. But that's not true because on Chesson Street, there's no setback. Well, it's not, it's not marked everywhere. But that's just what the vehicle code says. Just like you can't park 15 feet from a fire hydrant. So mine was the first one on Queen Street to get this. I'm sorry? My, my block and my, that corner there was the first one to get this on Queen
Street? First to get what on Queen Street? The setbacks. The pavement markings and the delineators? The pavement markings. The pavement markings and the posts? I guess the posts haven't gone in. No, on the streets. I mean, we've done it on many intersections throughout the city. I don't know of any. On Chester Street, it's right up to the crosswalk and following block and James Street, it's up to the crosswalk. I mean, it's more than every location.
It's, you know, it's part of the vehicle code. So we try to emphasize it at certain locations by putting those paper markings down.
Right. And as we do the work, that's as we do that enforcement as well.
I trust your opinion. My digging in is it doesn't do anything. It takes up parking spaces. That's what it does. It sets back people. Now you have on Lemon Street you still have two loading zones on Lemon Street at two different locations with no businesses. What happens there? Does that make sense?
What locations are those?
The one at Smiley's Deli that's a loading zone.
And it's a business?
Pardon me?
You had said that there were loading zones where there were no businesses.
Yeah, it's no business there. It's closed. It's been closed for two years.
Okay, what's the set up?
And the second one is at the apartment building right across the street where I'm at. They have a loading zone in the back in the garage. You go in the garage and you load all your furniture up and it goes up the elevator. Why is there two there? There's only a corner store and a hair salon there. And she only has one appointment a day.
and she you know her customers like $3,000 a day I mean if you see it's all
the pictures that I put up there you can see what's happening to that loading
zone I mean have people sleeping on the ground okay okay okay thank you very
much thanks thank you for your time so we haven't created a motion to have the
report I'm sorry I don't think we need I think we can just take action and it
will be consistent with the the loading zone somewhere in mid block depending on what the report indicates as well as confirmation of the handicapped spatial which I believe is already installed install it's okay many do you have all that very good thank you very much thank you very much very time so under this work says consider the request of the load zone this is a moot request because would be dealt with administratively the next item then is item 11-2025 consider the request of martin keene to restrict parking on abraham polite street senior avenue and cemetery avenue
yes good afternoon have you received the packet of information that i gave to mindy gable yes
it's extensive have you all read it i've read much of it and what i what i'm finding though is that it may be a again this may be a situation that we as a traffic commission don't have jurisdiction because it is not part of the public right of way because it's not what part of the
public right of way well actually it is and that's what i'm trying to to do with that is show that it is a public street and it has gone back and forth over 50 years that i've been involved with it that is private or public and i i don't understand what the city's problem is with it if it's not if it's not a public street then really no street in the city of lancaster is
public no most of the streets in the city of lancaster are public but this one for a variety of reasons including some of the information that you had submitted is indicated to not public street and we would not be able to act on it until it is until or unless it is designated a public street so we're it's not that we won't do yay or nay it says we're not the right entity to which you appeal to make sure that it is mapped as a public street so who do i go to
the city has threatened has threatened to take us to court and i said fine take us to court because because I know we'll win, because it has to be a city street, because it's the Hamilton lots. If it's not a city street, then streets such as Christian, Cherry, Mifflin, those cannot be city streets then, because they fall all under the same jurisdiction, the original layout of the streets before Pennsylvania was even a state. I mean, that became a public street in 1752.
guess the unfortunate thing is that this one has been in contention and we as traffic commission cannot take action on it unless and until it is made clear that it is designated as a public street so i i'm not in a position to argue okay like if if there's proof that can be presented with a with a certain i don't know survey certification that is so designated then we can act but right now what you're making is you're trying to make the case and we're not the entity
that adjudicates that type of a case well okay when i was talking with the city's council for this uh neil albert we agreed that it was they agreed it was a city street their only contention was the width of the street the city at that point in time that was their only contention
and they have not passed that on to you or no one seems to know that i will say that it was not documented that it was a city street that was an opinion not a not set then over the summer why
did the city patch some of the potholes it may have been a mistake no they've always they've
done it for years i think it's been a question of whether it's public or private and the documentation that you provided from the former mayor and public works director that it was private is what the city is going with because that's the last correspondence provided to you related to the status of the street so knowing that the people current uh dpw employees were not aware of that correspondence and once we became aware now we are treating it as a private street until it is proven
otherwise and there are a number of those throughout the city that are either private or shared alleys
okay it'll tie up the traffic some of the times then because we have to unload tractor trailers i mean we've been operating there for next year next year will be our 100th year of operating there so it'll just tie up the traffic when we have to unload tractor trailers
i would suggest is either through your your solicitor or ours seek the remedy what how do you get it designated one way or the other if it becomes a public street then we can talk about parking and how and where parking can or cannot be restricted but if it is not public we cannot or if it is not clear we cannot say okay this again it seems that this is administrative because we don't have authority to do anything on this on this particular item just to deny because because of jurisdiction deny for lack of
confirmation of jurisdiction so motion made is there a second any further
discussion all in favor any opposed thank you so the next new business item is item 12-20 25 consider the request of concerns regarding oversized vehicles parking on fremont street and that request is by oh this is a bit is this one ben one that you had
looked at yeah i think sergeant can provide sergeant yes yes i can um so this this came in um a couple different ways but uh nevertheless we did as the police department uh take a look at this um the vehicles are tow trucks we reached out i personally reached out to the tow truck owner advised him on the oversized vehicle ordinance in the city of leicester which states that these vehicles are not allowed to park on the street between the hours of 10 p.m and 2 excuse me and 6 a.m except for one hour at a time we did send out a representative of the department to advise One night in person, tires were marked, came back, the vehicles were still parked, tickets were issued. This complaint came in from a neighbor who also sent me photos of the vehicles parked out front. However, during the daylight hours, before the hours of 10 p.m., those vehicles being parked on the street are legally parked. And this was related to all parties that the ordinance clearly states 10 p.m. Monday through Friday and at midnight on the weekends that the vehicles are not allowed to be parked other than one hour on the streets. These are not commercial vehicles. They do not exceed the weight of 26,000 pounds. But these vehicles do have a gross vehicle weight. And based on the way the ordinance is written, gross vehicle weight is what they are permitted to tow. So they exceed that gross vehicle weight, all vehicles in question.
So is it a matter that there needs to be signage here, or what's the best way for it to be enforced?
So enforcement is only permitted based on the ordinance after 10 p.m.
Okay.
So during the daytime, as you see the pictures here, the tow trucks are parked. They're legally parked. So like I said, they do not fall under the commercial vehicle designation. designation. So you could post the, you know, no commercial vehicle signs just as they're posted in 11 o'clock, but it wouldn't apply to these particular vehicles. So the best way to enforce is either to have people constantly call or have two or three blasts where they're ticketed and get the message. So the correspondence I had back and forth was that it was resolved, at least for that period of time. um like speaking to the tow truck owners they were willing to move their vehicles have their small tow truck there parked to the rear of the property as long as it was uh part of an approved path for parking within the residence um so at this point in time i hadn't heard anything else from uh the person who had initially lodged a complaint it would take some follow-up if to see whether they're still having an issue but again it's happening at night you know that's at the time that we can actually, you know, bring any sort of enforcement and quite frankly, people just aren't up in the middle of the night looking out their window to see if there's a tow truck park there. Council member, you
had, you had brought part of this to our attention. I think you had reached out to see if there were residents who were willing to come and speak. Yes,
but I didn't. I would have to schedule for her to come in to see because she does work, so she's not able to come around this time. But she did bring it to my attention. And the elderlies that are living on the opposite direction that the neighbor question was, they're elderly, and they had to get to garages in order to avoid the constant trying to get parking, because those tow trucks are there.
it seems like it's more like it's an enforcement issue um which means that please correct me if this is not the appropriate strategy that in the short term since they are not illegally parked during that day when they are illegally parked one needs to call for them to be ticketed and hopefully that gets the message across that they are not to be parking there when they're not supposed to park correct
i would say that would be um our only course of action at this point of time uh outside of you know a new ordinance being rewritten
um and that's if there were new ordinance rewritten you would have to address this kind of a situation in several other locations you would have to talk about the category of truck it would have to be different a different threshold of weight category which we I don't believe we have that separate category at this time so it's a matter of enforcement do you have a sense of clarity what kind of
enforcement well if they have a park there when the majority of the community that comes home from work and they do have to move it in order for them to have the space there to park so I would say they'd have to move it out of the
area in order for them to have access to parking yes that's not that's not something we can enforce because they're legally parked at that point in time like i said well isn't the size i mean i know
that there is a certain weight and size that they're not supposed to be part of it so the
oversize again the way the organs is written the overweight and oversized it is about the weight it's not the overall dimension of the vehicle it's so it's the weight of the vehicle these vehicles are not blocking any sight lines or near a stop sign or anything like that causing a hazard or preventing people from seeing signage they're they're just parked and i know it's inconvenient and it's it's not courteous um but again it's not illegal either i will let her know
and we'll see if there's anything else additional we can do to make changes
I think part of it may be having clarity in the immediate neighborhood of what to do and when these vehicles are allowed and when they're not allowed, so that one gets into the right rhythm, but also enforcing the trucks not being there when they're not supposed to be there, so that there's greater flexibility in terms of parking availability.
And that information, again, was provided. I'm just curious as to how recent this complaint has kind of come to your attention, just because, like I said, we did put a decent amount of effort into resolving this problem.
I think she said that she had forwarded to Mr. Campbell a year ago, so this is a continual.
Okay. Like I said, I spoke to her in January of this year. And like I said, I don't have the dates on when we issued tickets, but we did issue tickets on all of our tow trucks, which the vehicle owner called me, upset about it, obviously, responded to the station, spoke to the desk sergeant. uh, sort of consider also spoke to, um, the total tow truck over because they are one of our proof totals and advise them on what the ordinance is and what the expectation was. So, um, I don't mind following up with her to see if the problem still is persisting or if it hasn't been resolved. That would be
great. That would be great. Um, and maybe letting her know that they, that they were taking it because maybe she feels like nobody has been listening to
She was aware because I know then there was the call came back about one of her vehicles, which was legally parked as well. So it just became a back and forth between, you know, neighbors at that point in time. But like I said, we did our best to try to handle the situation at that point in time based on the parameters that we're able to function in.
So it would be greatly appreciated if you can follow through and see if that situation has changed. Now that the weather is changing, it may be something that needs to be repeated in order to reinforce to people that they shouldn't be parking here. Yes. When they're not allowed to be parking there, but get into the right rhythm of it. Correct. Thank you. so is there any further action to be taken on that particular item
none of this time it's administratively addressed
this is being addressed administratively as well no action is necessary so that completes our new business action agenda the next is the consent agenda and traditionally what we've done is look at each of these items and there's one item 13-2025 science having been tentatively approved or installed item 14-2025 following signs have been removed item 15-2025 conditional temporary parking permits have been issued by lpa and item 16-2025 conditional temporary parking permits have been asked for continuance we often either take them individually or as a group as a single motion unless there's and to my recollection there has not been any challenge uh for any of the addresses listed so i'm either waiting for a motion for one of them or a motion for all a motion for all the motion has been introduced for all is there a second second motion in the second is there any discussion for the discussion all in favor aye aye the motion carries so all the consent agenda items have been passed is there any any additional business that needs to come before the commission um having said that the the agenda of the traffic commission FOR MARCH 11TH HAS BEEN COMPLETED DO I HEAR A MOTION TO ADJOURN SO MOVED THIS MOTION AND ALL IN FAVOR AYE AYE MOTION CARRIES THANK YOU VERY MUCH